Guide to Socialist Party of Montana records 1907-1950, bulk 1910-1918
Montana Historical Society Research Center
Socialist Party of Montana records
1907-1950
bulk 1910-1918
Montana Historical Society Archives
MF 425
Socialist Party (Mont.)
2 reels of film
Records (1899-1950) of the Socialist Party of Montana include general correspondence, primarily from the Bozeman and Missoula locals; subject files on Butte socialist mayor Lewis Duncan, the National Finnish Socialist Organization, the National Women's Committee of the Socialist Party, and the Party's relationship with the Montana State Federation of Labor from 1929 to 1950; organizational records; reports; and printed materials.
The Socialist Party of America was formed in 1901 by a merger of the Social Democratic party of America and portions of the Socialist Labor Party. In 1903, socialists in Montana elected the mayor, treasurer, police judge and three councilmen in the city of Anaconda. With that impetus, the Socialist Party of Montana spread rapidly, predominantly in Butte and other industrial towns, but also among farmers in many small communities. By 1912, there were members of the party in sixty-seven Montana communities. In 1911, Butte elected a Socialist city government, headed by Mayor Lewis Duncan. With the industrial turmoil in Butte, and with the coming of World War I, the party declined rapidly after 1917.
This collection contains correspondence, subject files, financial records, organizational records, and more. The bulk of the general correspondence relates to the locals, and most of that material is from Bozeman and Missoula. The locals corresponded about organizing, elections, and financial problems. The remainder of the correspondence concerns "organizers- speakers," who traveled around the state, and the executive committee.
The subject files include material on Butte and Butte socialist Mayor, Lewis Duncan, the National Finnish Socialist Organization, the National Women's Committee of the Socialist Party, and the Party's relationship with the Montana State Federation of Labor (1929-1950). The organizational records include minutes of the state party and Butte local; and national party platforms, bulletins, and referenda. The reports are "organizers-speakers" reports on meetings conducted around the state and the nation; and reports of the state parliamentary committee. The printed material series includes miscellaneous copies of the Montana Socialist, published in Missoula in 1946.
This collection is arranged into seven series: 1) General Correspondence, 2) Subject Files, 3) Financial Records, 4) Organizational Records, 5) Reports, 6) Miscellany, and 7) Printed Materials.
Collection is open for research.
Acquisition information available upon request.
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the Montana Historical Society Archives catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search under these terms.
Socialism--Montana.
Montana--Politics and government.
Montana
Detailed Description of the Collection
- General Correspondence
  - Absarokee, 1912 (Reel 1 / 1)
  - Basin, referendum, 1910-1912 (Reel 1 / 2)
  - Beaverton (illegible), undated (Reel 1 / 3)
  - Billings, 1910-1918 (Reel 1 / 4)
  - Bonner, 1910 (Reel 1 / 5)
  - Bozeman, 1910 (Reel 1 / 6)
  - Busteed, 1912 (Reel 1 / 7)
  - Butte, 1910 (Reel 1 / 8)
  - Butte (Finnish), 1910 (Reel 1 / 9)
  - Chico, charter only, undated (Reel 1 / 10)
  - Chinook, 1912 (Reel 1 / 11)
  - Columbia Falls, membership list only, undated (Reel 1 / 12)
  - Columbus, membership list only, undated (Reel 1 / 13)
  - Conrad, 1911 (Reel 1 / 14)
  - Cut Bank, undated (Reel 1 / 15)
  - Deer Lodge, 1910 (Reel 1 / 16)
  - Dillon, 1910 (Reel 1 / 17)
  - Ekalaka, 1910-1912 (Reel 1 / 18)
  - Fairfield, 1912 (Reel 1 / 19)
  - Forest Grove, 1910 (Reel 1 / 20)
  - Fortine, membership list only, 1910 (Reel 1 / 21)
  - Fromberg, 1910 (Reel 1 / 22)
  - Great Falls, 1910-1916 (Reel 1 / 23)
  - Hamilton, 1910-1916 (Reel 1 / 24)
  - Harlowton, 1912 (Reel 1 / 25)
  - Harrison (barely legible), 1911 (Reel 1 / 26)
  - Havre, 1911 (Reel 1 / 27)
  - Helena, 1910-1915 (Reel 1 / 28)
  - Helena (Finnish), membership list and letter, 1911 (Reel 1 / 29)
  - Heron, 1914-1916 (Reel 1 / 30)
  - Highwood, 1916-1917 (Reel 1 / 31)
  - Hoffman, membership list only, undated (Reel 1 / 32)
  - Inverness, 1910-1916 (Reel 1 / 33)
  - Kendall, 1911 (Reel 1 / 34)
  - Lake Como, 1910 (Reel 1 / 35)
  - Laurel, 1910 (Reel 1 / 36)
  - Lavina, 1910 (Reel 1 / 37)
  - Lewistown, 1911 (Reel 1 / 38)
  - Libby, membership list and letters, 1910 (Reel 1 / 39)
  - Manhattan, membership list and letters, 1910-1911 (Reel 1 / 40)
  - Martinsdale, 1909-1910 (Reel 1 / 41)
  - Miles City, 1910-1911 (Reel 1 / 42)
  - Missoula, 1910-1912 (Reel 1 / 43)
  - Monarch, membership list only, 1910 (Reel 1 / 44)
  - Mondak, membership list and letters, 1910-1911 (Reel 1 / 45)
  - Moore, 1911 (Reel 1 / 46)
  - Norris, 1911 (Reel 1 / 47)
  - Orville, 1912 (Reel 1 / 48)
  - Ovando, 1910-1912 (Reel 1 / 49)
  - Philipsburg, 1910 (Reel 1 / 50)
  - Plentywood, 1910 (Reel 1 / 51)
  - Polson, 1910 (Reel 1 / 52)
  - Radersburg, 1910 (Reel 1 / 53)
  - Red Lodge, 1910-1915 (Reel 1 / 54)
  - Rollins, 1911-1912 (Reel 1 / 55)
  - Roundup (barely legible), 1911 (Reel 1 / 56)
  - St. Regis, 1910 (Reel 1 / 57)
  - Salesville, 1910-1911 (Reel 1 / 58)
  - Stark, 1911 (Reel 1 / 59)
  - Sweetgrass, 1911 (Reel 1 / 60)
  - Toston, 1910-1911 (Reel 1 / 61)
  - Troy, 1910 (Reel 1 / 62)
  - Twin Bridges, 1912 (Reel 1 / 63)
  - Washoe, membership list only, 1911 (Reel 1 / 64)
  - Whitehall, 1910 (Reel 1 / 65)
  - Wickes, undated (Reel 1 / 66)
  - Zortman, membership list and letter, 1910-1911 (Reel 1 / 67)
  - Members at large, 1912 (Reel 1 / 68)
  - Executive Committee, 1910-1911 (Reel 1 / 69)
  - State organizers / speakers (J. Frank Mable), 1910-1912 (Reel 1 / 70)
  - State organizers / speakers (Albert F. Meissner), 1912 (Reel 1 / 71)
  - State organizers / speakers (William Raoul), 1911-1912 (Reel 1 / 71)
  - State Secretary (Louis Duncan), 1910-1912 (Reel 1 / 73-75)
  - State Secretary (re routing speakers), 1910-1912 (Reel 1 / 76)
  - National campaign investigating committee, 1911-1912 (Reel 2 / 77)
  - Organizers / speakers (includes W. G. Henry), 1910 (Reel 2 / 78)
- Subject Files
  - Butte Mine Workers' Union: membership and dues rolls, 1914 (Reel 2 / 79)
  - Butte Socialist Publishing Company, 1911-1913 (Reel 2 / 80)
  - Butte Workingmen’s Union membership list, 1910 (Reel 2 / 81)
  - Lewis J. Duncan, Mayor of Butte, congratulatory letters, 1911 (Reel 2 / 82)
  - Lewis J. Duncan, Mayor of Butte, miscellaneous, 1911-1914 (Reel 2 / 83)
  - James D. Graham – Ida Crouch Hazlett controversies (re Montana News), 1910-1912 (Reel 2 / 84)
  - James D. Graham, State Secretary of Montana Socialist Party and President of Montana State Federation of Labor, 1940-1950 (Reel 2 / 85)
  - National Finnish Socialist Organization, 1910-1911 (Reel 2 / 86)
  - National Women’s Committee of the Socialist Party, 1910-1912 (Reel 2 / 87)
  - Clippings (re socialism), undated (Reel 2 / 88)
- Financial Records
  - Butte local #1, miscellaneous, 1908 (Reel 2 / 89)
  - State party, cancelled checks, 1910 (Reel 2 / 90)
  - State party, financial statements and reports, undated (Reel 2 / 91)
  - State party, receipts, 1910 (Reel 2 / 92)
  - National party, financial reports, 1910 (Reel 2 / 93)
- Organizational Records
  - Constitution of Socialist Party of Colorado, undated (Reel 2 / 94)
  - Constitution of Socialist Party of Butte local (barely legible), 1913 (Reel 2 / 95)
  - Constitutions of Socialist Party of Montana, 1908-1914 (Reel 2 / 96)
  - Minutes of Butte local (barely legible), 1907-1909 (Reel 2 / 97)
  - Butte local petition to Executive Committee, 1913 (Reel 2 / 98)
  - Local referendum vote for State Secretary, undated (Reel 2 / 99)
  - Montana Socialist Party convention minutes, includes report of Executive Committee (portions barely legible), 1910 (Reel 2 / 100)
  - Montana Socialist Party Executive Committee minutes, 1910-1911 (Reel 2 / 101)
  - Montana Socialist Party referendums, 1910 (Reel 2 / 102)
  - National party weekly bulletins, 1910 (Reel 2 / 103)
  - Socialist Party platforms, 1910-1934 (Reel 2 / 104)
- Reports
  - Local branches tabulated reports, 1910-1911 (Reel 2 / 105)
  - Montana Socialist Party organizers: speakers reports (Lewis Duncan, J. Frank Mable, Albert F. Meissner, William Raoul), 1912 (Reel 2 / 106)
  - State Parliamentary Committee reports, 1914 (Reel 2 / 107)
  - National party organizers: speakers' reports, 1913 (Reel 2 / 108)
- Miscellany
  - Miscellaneous bills and laws, 1907 (Reel 2 / 109)
- Printed Materials
  - Labor and Socialist Press News, 1929 (Reel 2 / 110)
  - Montana General Election returns (not filmed), 1924 (Reel 2 / 111)
  - Montana Socialist (Missoula) scattered issues, 1946 (Reel 2 / 112)